<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-07-17T21:32:56+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Andreas Ringedal - UX Designer and Researcher</title><subtitle>Andreas Ringedal is a self-employed UX Design and Research consultant based in Sweden. He specializes in design from a user and usability perspective. Main competences are concept design, usability studies and user experience design. Oh, he is also a front-end developer.</subtitle><author><name>Andreas Ringedal</name></author><entry><title type="html">Turbu+</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/astrazeneca/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Turbu+" /><published>2017-07-14T13:20:34+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-14T13:20:34+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/astrazeneca</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/astrazeneca/">&lt;p class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;Information provided here does not necessarily reflect the views of AstraZeneca or inUse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you get when you mix Medtech, IoT and asthma?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turbu+&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By attaching a small device to your asthma inhaler you can easily track your daily inhalations and get reminders on your phone if you missed one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;goals&quot;&gt;Goals:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design new solutions for existing product&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deliver wireframes and user stories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Act as support for decisions regarding UX and design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider Medtech regulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked together with colleagues from inUse with implementing new functionality for the Turbu+ solution. It is a complex service with many stakeholders and regulations such as patient data privacy. Turbu+ is supported for various markets hence the solution had to support multi-languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;platforms&quot;&gt;Platforms:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;iOS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Android&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Web&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app itself is meant for end users but in addition, there is a web portal for doctors who can track their patient’s data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this release, the main focus was on self-enrollment and symptom tracking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-enrollment was heavier from the technical viewpoint. From a user perspective, it was a fairly simple sign-up process. What we did include in the onboarding process though, were instructions on how to assemble the device and pair it with the phone via Bluetooth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Symptom tracking is done by the user and the idea of symptom tracking itself is complex hence everyone is different and experience his or her symptoms in different ways. We spoke to specialists in the field to boil it down to something tangible and useful for the users. Some weeks before the project deadline, the managers decided to bring in a ready solution for symptom tracking due to the fact that it was clinically tested and approved. A major factor for companies in the medical field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The upside was that our solutions were more or less the same, at least an ego boost. The flipside was that our UI patterns were completely different. Reminding time of the project we focused on finding ways for how to implement the ready solutions and make sure it would have a look and feel which reminded of the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tools&quot;&gt;Tools:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sketch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Principle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;inVision&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zeplin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Process
We worked in-house with the creative process. Sketching, thinking and interviewing. At the end of every deadline, we presented ideas and made proposals. Always one sprint ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For every successful sign-off, we then produced wireframes, visual assets and guidelines for developers to implement. I also took on the challenge of animating the app using Principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/astrazeneca-turbu-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Phones with Turbu+ App&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as the updated version of the app is released I will add more visuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;in-retrospect&quot;&gt;In retrospect:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are many regulations within the healthcare&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The art of getting your design approved when dealing with a lot of stakeholders&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arguing for the impact of design in a fairly conservative market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to merge two completely different apps into one’s such an interesting field with endless possibilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Andreas Ringedal</name></author><summary type="html">UX/UI Design</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My AEG App</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/electrolux/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My AEG App" /><published>2016-07-14T13:20:34+02:00</published><updated>2016-07-14T13:20:34+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/electrolux</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/electrolux/">&lt;p class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;Information provided here does not necessarily reflect the views of Electrolux or inUse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electrolux is transitioning into the digital era by making connectivity and Internet of Things a priority. They had a low-fidelity interactive prototype for controlling a washing machine via a smartphone app. I was hired together with a colleague to perform usability tests, highlight problems and make suggestions for improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/electrolux-aeg-app-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Three phones with prototype interface used for usability testing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;goals&quot;&gt;Goals:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Write scripts and questionnaires&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set test environment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perform tests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify problem areas with the app&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deliver test summary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always when it comes to usability testing (which is also the fun part), be prepared for the unexpected and be totally open towards how other resonate. For these tests, a methodology developed by designers from Electrolux were used, measuring effectiveness, efficiency and satisfaction for every task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/acreo-ux-lab-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Acreo UX lab&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tests were done in Acreo’s UX Lab in Stockholm. When arranging the setting we gave top priority to catch and record the phone’s screen to see how participants interacted as well as looking at hand gestures. Secondly, we had one camera focusing on the face to catch facial expressions. The microphone was hidden in the towel behind the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/acreo-ux-lab-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Acreo UX lab&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cameras, microphones and a big see-through mirror for spectators to watch the test. Although participants weren’t aware of the number of people watching they did sense the presence of others. It was a challenge to make participants feel comfortable doing the test, especially for the part when they pretended to operate the washing machine by clicking on a paper prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/acreo-ux-lab-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Acreo UX lab&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, you quickly get a feeling for what most participants are going to struggle with. It’s easy to judge too quickly and draw conclusions but as long as you continue to ask open questions and make sure the participant is thinking aloud, the unexpected insights will come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;test-procedure&quot;&gt;Test procedure:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Background questionnaire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Initial exploration to capture first interaction and impressions, expectations and mental model for the UI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Task scenarios,  collecting data of performance, effectiveness and efficiency.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Satisfaction questionnaire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Semi-structured post-use interview&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;in-retrospect&quot;&gt;In retrospect:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Usability testing is necessary and fun&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is how you catch the unexpected insights early&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A well-structured test and report have a bigger impact within the organization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/electrolux-aeg-app-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Phone with AEG My App interface&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Andreas Ringedal</name></author><summary type="html">Usability testing</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MEMOPlanner</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/abilia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MEMOPlanner" /><published>2015-07-14T13:20:34+02:00</published><updated>2015-07-14T13:20:34+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/abilia</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/abilia/">&lt;p class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;Information provided here does not necessarily reflect the views of Abilia or Sigma IT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the web really for everyone? No, it’s not. There is a group of people who are foreseen by not being able to browse websites nor use apps because of their special needs. Abilia develop products to make sure these people become more independent and can take control of their everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was Design Lead in the work with developing the new version of MEMOPlanner, helping people with cognitive impairments become more independent in their life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;goals&quot;&gt;Goals:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Redesign MEMOPlanner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design new UI patterns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep key features&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deliver graphics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Craft wireframes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put together a design guideline for the developers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/abilia-memoplanner-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tablet with MEMOPlanner app&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person with a cognitive disorder can be affected in different ways. Abilities such as learning, memory, perception and problem solving can be heavily reduced. Not being able to structure the day might lead to stress and anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a scattered user group as there is a wide spectrum of how functional users are. Some people need a friendly reminder about daily activities while others need help with remembering what day it is and getting help with when to eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/abilia-memoplanner-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tablet with MEMOPlanner app&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;process&quot;&gt;Process:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research user group&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Define hypotheses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iterate concepts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Final design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to regulations, no usability testing could be done with the main target group until afterwards. Decisions were made based on design hypotheses sprung from research and best praxis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started by reading literature and interviewing internally, focusing on the difference between mild and severe cognitive disabilities and the general problem people within the spectrum experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That led me to define several design hypotheses which would guide me during the concept phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tools&quot;&gt;Tools:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Balsamiq&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photoshop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Illustrator&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;InVision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here it continued as an agile project as I started working with the technical and product management side. I was one sprint ahead with designing graphics. Together we defined functionality simultaneously as I iterated concepts for managers to sign off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;platforms&quot;&gt;Platforms:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Android&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Web&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/abilia-memoplanner-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tablet with MEMOPlanner app&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MEMOPlanner was launched in December 2016 and have been praised by its users ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;in-retrospect&quot;&gt;In retrospect:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Define specific and measurable goals together with the client&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Define personal expectations and ask for the same&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use internal knowledge but dare to challenge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everyone has the right to have a digital life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/f8E_wsJEo2s?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;436px&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Andreas Ringedal</name></author><summary type="html">Design Lead</summary></entry></feed>